18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: ambassador.
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: First of all, thank you, everyone, for joining for this seminar. I'll just give a brief introduction of our instructors, for the upcoming course. Dr. Karan Mitelki, who has been very, very active in the space of Aswin Jodhis for more than six, seven years. He has completed his, by provision, completed his master's in
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: and doctors, MBBS, and at the same time, his MS in Vastu and Psychology. And he has been guiding a lot of people on both practical and theoretical basis, both instructing on Vastu and guiding people as well. And we also have, Goin Pravuji with us.
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: who has been working in the field of Indian knowledge system education, including Mahabharat, including Vastu, Jyotesh.
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: An integrated… an integrated psychology for more than 2 decades, 3 decades right now.
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: With this, I'd like to warmly hand over to Dr. Karan Mitelji and Goin Prabhuji for the sessions ahead.
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: Thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Today, everyone, and I welcome you all. Firstly, thank you, Suraji, for the introduction, and I welcome you all for this 5-day masterclass.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Without much delay, I would like to kind of use or share a PPD so that we can flow together in the course and build on the concept slowly. So just give me a moment, and…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, basically, the way the course has been designed is we'll kind of try to cover the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: We'll not get into too much of theory and the philosophical aspects of Jyotish and Vastu, but we'll try to cover the conceptualizations that these Shastras began with, and kind of how these Shastras expanded, and how they are relevant
Dr. Karan Mittal: to our life in our day-to-day practices, etc. What are the limitations, and where the shastas can be useful. So that's how… and also, we'll try to kind of get into the practical aspects of, of course, doing vasto, at least for our own causes, towards the end of the, like, session 3, 4, 5, and also understanding the language of astrology as the course.
Dr. Karan Mittal: mentioned, like, trying to understand what is the language of astrology, what are rishis meant, what was the limitation that they had already prescribed in Shastas, where we currently
Dr. Karan Mittal: in the astrologic perspective, overclaim. So, these are the basic things, and also we'll kind of try to look at our charts and try to kind of make some sense of what exactly our chart is speaking, and where we can combine
Dr. Karan Mittal: astrology and Vasu for the betterment of our lungs. So, basically.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We'll be doing a full-fledged vastru of our own houses, and also we'll integrate it with the astrological chart that we have, at least the person staying in the house, and also how these two concepts relate to our psychological well-being. So that's the basic framework of the course, and without much delay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Let's… let's kind of begin with… with… the material.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when we see the traditional grantas of astrology, or even with Vastu, one thing is very clear that Rishis kind of conceptualized these two Shastras to understand what are the possibilities or the probabilities that are there in future.
Dr. Karan Mittal: it was never mentioned… it was never meant to kind of overclaim, it was never meant to kind of say that only this will happen. Of course, with their intuitive
Dr. Karan Mittal: see your, like, intuitive guidance, etc. Many rishis and many saints have predicted things, but as a Shastra, it was meant to kind of predict the possibilities that hold in future, and also kind of align our decisions based on the possibilities that we have. So, if the possibilities of, like, 50% or 60% or something, aligning our decisions and our karma or our deeds into that 50-60% can push it
Dr. Karan Mittal: to 70, 80, 90%, and that holds for Jyotish also, and that holds for Vasco also. If your house is compatible to probably 60-70%, doing the Vastu remedies that Shasta has prescribed before starting the house at Sutta makes the positivity or the compatibility of the house to 70, 80, 90%. And if the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Vastuv has doshas, then doing the remedies also, you cannot guarantee, you know, that the whole thing will be solved completely, but it will reduce the negative effect that a particular dosha will have in her life. So, it was not to kind of escape fate, it was not to kind of ditch the fate, it was not to kind of change everything, top down, like, completely change everything.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It was to understand what holds in the future, what are the possibilities, what are our paramptas that we are born with, and trying to align our this life accordingly, so that the person could pursue the four Kurshartas in a better way.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, and also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If we go to the very textual or very shastric side of integrating Jyotesha, Ayurveda, and all the sciences that are there for the well-being of the human, we'll see that Guran Karma, and Jammuar, these are the three aspects that Rishis speak about.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Guna is basically your traits, your characteristics, your attributes, we all know that, sattvarajas, tamas, all that stuff. Karma is what we do, and Jammu is basically the time you were born… time you were born, and that is your astrological state.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sold.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Astrology basically is a science that uses the principle of Jammu, that is the principle of the astrological chart, or your kunli, to understand your Guna and karma.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what are your innate characteristics, attributes, and what would be your karma?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Based on your product, etc, in this life, and kind of making… synchronizing both of them for, you know, kind of taking the maximum benefit of this life, whether it is for Dharma orthrakama, or naksha. So that was the conceptualization of Rishi. What we did was, or what the modern day
Dr. Karan Mittal: astrology is doing is, we are taking Jammu, we are taking the remedies from different, different, you know, shastras, or creating our own remedies, and we are saying that this remedy, when done, will change your Gurna also, will change your karma also completely 100%. That doesn't hold true in astrology. In fact.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you speak to very traditional astrologers who have studied for generations and generations, they will talk about remedies which are, of course, very shastric, like a japa, dhana.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, Yagya. And they will say that even after doing that, don't expect that this particular dosha will vanish completely. It will kind of become, you know, it will reduce in its intensity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It will show lesser effects on your life, but still, you'll have to kind of go through that dosha to some or the other extent. And also, they classify it into different intensities, manda, Madhya, and thibra, praraab, etc, and they speak about this. So, whatever we see today as a
Dr. Karan Mittal: as a solution or a remedy in astrology of Vasco. It claims 100%, but it's never 100%. It could be good for the psychological, psychological belief that, okay, I've done this remedy and things would change, but Shastra's never came with it
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you could take over the admitting of the participants, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so Gwena, tarma, and Jharma. So, Gwena, we already spoke the temperament, the traits, the characteristics. Tarma is what we do, okay? Our deeds, basically, and Jammu is basically your birth chart, and astrology kind of reveals these two different aspects to us.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Through a probability method, not through a confirmatory method, but through a probability method.
Dr. Karan Mittal: how do we claim, like, of course, we'll not get into too much of depth, but how does… how does this Shastra, this science, evolve, in… in our… in our Rishi Parampara? So, whenever we talk about
Dr. Karan Mittal: gaining knowledge in Shastas. We'll not get into the philosophical depth of it, but there are three means of knowledge that we talk about. One is prathaksha, that we see through eyes, ear, through our ears, smell, taste, whatever can be obtained through our senses, that's in the Pragaksha Pramana.
Dr. Karan Mittal: An umanav is where we infer something, like, if you see a smoke, you infer there is fire, okay? And Shabda is, because we cannot process all the knowledge that is there in the world by our own
Dr. Karan Mittal: self in one lifetime. That's why we kind of believe the Shastras, believe the bona fide master, and kind of take those words and carry it forward. And astrology is basically… or astrology Vasdu is basically based on all three pramanas. What we do is, we make it fully a Shavna Brahmana. We say that this astrologer has said this, this, this, this, this. That's my… that means it's like, it's a Brahmavakya, and that's how it will happen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or this was through Shastri ascent. But that's not it, how it developed itself.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Firstly, the movement of planets and stars were kind of understood by our Rishis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Firstly, in their meditative state, and secondly, they observe. There are mentions of making, you know, observatories and ashastras, how to kind of find the east and the west direction by using shadow method. So they observed how sun, moon, everything moved over the years, and started doing the mathematical calculation. That's the Pratakshaprahman.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, it is so deep in our Shastras that if you now… if you come to the Vastu part, you will see that we… we all know that sun rises in the east and sets in west, that's easy. But in Vastu, it is said that
Dr. Karan Mittal: A house shouldn't have more windows in the south direction, okay?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, logically, the Shastras, now, like, Shastri Klifier, I go just as per Shabbra Pramana, they say it gives rise to health issues, okay? But now, if you go from the Prataksha Pramana perspective, they saw that the sun rises in the east, and then it travels to the west, sorry, it travels to the west through the south.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when the house has too many windows in the south direction, automatically the aggressive sun of the known
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or the later known, or the early known, the, the sun rides, the sun, rays of that, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: intensity or that aggression will come into the house from the south direction, the southeaster direction, etc. So, the temperature of this house will automatically rise, and definitely it will rise… give rise to, you know, a sense of discomfort, sense of feeling the heat, more sweating, more psychological disturbance, because too much of heat also disturbs a person. But they also said that you need to have more windows in the north and the northeast, because they knew
Dr. Karan Mittal: that the indirect sunlight, like, you need light in the house, so rather than having the direct light into the house, that indirect light. So, we have already decided, regardless of that. If your house has too many windows in the south, then it's needed that you keep the windows also, you keep the curtains closed during the afternoon or the noon, because you need to avoid
Dr. Karan Mittal: getting in… Too much of sunlight of that particular time of the day.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Shastrikli also, and as per the Pratish Pramana. But they said that more windows in the north was useful, because… because that's the indirect sunlight that comes to your house, and then house automatically has the light to read, and two different… two different tools. So that's how the Pratish Pramana worked. They observed the moments. Then there was Anumana, that is inference.
Dr. Karan Mittal: based on the movement, seeing the activities that happen in the nature, and seeing the activities that happen in every person's life, they started making permutations and combinations. We see so many times in Shastras that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Parashal Muni has said something about this combination, some other Rishi has said something about this planetary combination. So it's not contradictory, it's based on their experience, what they saw in the meditation, what they experienced, and they have listed down their combinations. And that's what we look in the horoscope. So there is definitely an inference involved, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's how the… that's how…
Dr. Karan Mittal: it runs even today. The number of careers that were there in that time were very limited. Today, we have different… millions of careers, probably, or thousands of careers. So how do we
Dr. Karan Mittal: How do the astrologists of today find out that, okay, a biomedical engineer should have
Dr. Karan Mittal: this particular combination. A neurosurgeon has… or a CA has to have this particular combination, because they kind of carried forward the Parampara of Anamana to today's world. And the last shast… that's the verbal testimony, or the bakke of the guru, or the Shastra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, because we cannot do the both Pratearchy and Umana in one lifetime, we take the experience from the previous acharyas and carry it forward.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it was never a Shastra which was kind of fully, you know, seen and meditated, and it came as an intuition. There has been mathematical calculations, there have been inferences, there have been various permutations, combinations, before the Shastra came for human well-being. So, that's why when we
Dr. Karan Mittal: try to…
Dr. Karan Mittal: understand astrology of Wastel. For our well-being, you cannot take it like a shaveda Pramana. It's not that if it says so, it will happen. And that's where Targetscha and Anumana come into nature.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, Govind Privu will speak about this, but as we know that karma is of two parts. In astrology also, if you read, it's of two parts. One is which we cannot understand, so… so… because it's so complicated. In fact, in the Shaneshastra, karma is called as Adrishta, that which cannot be seen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, which cannot be seen and understood. So, there's a part of Dharma which cannot be understood, and then there is a part that can be understood, manipulated, worked upon, and all the remedies that we do.
Dr. Karan Mittal: can… can… can, you know, change that particular part of it. So, astrology works on both. There are certain possibilities, or even Vasco. There are certain possibilities that cannot be changed. There are certain doshas that cannot be changed, how much ever remedies you
Dr. Karan Mittal: And there are certain things that are under your control. By doing different, different kinds of memories, you are able to change. So it's a balance between both the schools of thought. We cannot say that the conli is the final verdict.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And you cannot say… you can also not say that doing… by doing this 70 all year, or by doing so many japas, or so many ideas, everything in a country will get served. So that's how the balance works.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, how do we kind of look at the chart? In fact, I would request you all to kind of, in the next, 5 days, have at least your own personal chart, the Lagner chart. We'll discuss how to get to it towards the end of the lecture.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In front of you, maybe make it on a paper or have it on a screen. And also, maybe fetch your house layouts, for the vast part of the course, like the architects, or the interior's layout, or the building layout.
Dr. Karan Mittal: which kind of concerns your flat or your house, kind of fetch it so that we can also do some practical work as we go through the next 2 or 3 weeks. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, that's what… I will not get, again, into too much of the depth of it, but chart is a mirror. It's not like a verdict. It gives you the probabilities. It gives you what exactly holds, or what you… where are you placed at the current moment in your life, but it's not a verdict that, okay, 5 years down the line, or 10 years down the line, only this can happen. That's not possible.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this course basically is based on one significant principle of astrology, Vashturu, or maybe our Shastras, is Jadpindetan Brahmani.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the sense, what's in the universe reflects in your pin, that is, in your body. So, it kind of tries to align your inner psychology, that is the placement of the nine planets, or the areas that nine planets govern in your life, in your body, in your psyche.
Dr. Karan Mittal: with your immediate surroundings, the nine planets and the elements in your surroundings, that is a vastru, that is a house, which tries to align with the universal placement of the nine planets and the five elements, that is your astrological chart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we try to align these three aspects, and that kind of leads to the alignment of your… or the alignment of your inner selves. You align your decisions and
Dr. Karan Mittal: your karma as per your chart. You align the house as per what you need and provide your traits, characteristics, etc, and that kind of leads to that inner benevolent action, or inner well-being that we are kind of eyeing this post. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, basically, as I said, you will need
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably your work chart, that is 11 chart, and also the house layout for this course for the next four sessions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So basically, how do I see it? It's like, I see it like we are talking about our own self, and there are three different windows of looking at your own self. One is
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably, looking from the Vascular, or the house perspective, things around you. One is a chart perspective, and one is your inner… inner planetary positions perspective. So we are trying to look at the room from three different windows. So, definitely the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: As from the window you look in, you might see the room in a different way, but still, the things inside the room will still be the same. So your perspective might change, but the things inside the room will always stay the same.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what is a Jammakundi? So, we get to the course proper. What is a Jemma Kundi, or what's a horoscope? Basically, the time when you are born. It's basically the planetary positions in the universe, or in the solar system at that point of time. That's the basic definition of a horoscope. When a person is born.
Dr. Karan Mittal: At that particular point of time, which planet is placed in which particular Rashi, that is, which particular zodiac sign, which Rashi is where.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what is… what is there in the east direction, what is there in the west direction, south, north, etc. That's basically your Lagu chart. That's basically your base… the basic chart that we are kind… that all astrologers kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: use preliminary. Apart from that, then, of course, the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: once you go ahead, you kind of become more deeper into astrology, then there are different permutations and combinations of charts also that develop. But basically, this is the chart which kind of tells you the position of the solar system at that particular point of time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, suppose someone is born on…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Probably 15th of November 2000, at 1PM in Mumbai. Then…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the astrological chart is, at that particular point of time in Mumbai, what was the configuration of the solar system, at 1PM on 15th of November 2000, as per Mumbai. So… so it's basically a frozen photograph of the planets in the solar system at that point of time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now, when you kind of look at your chart, if you have your charts, please fetch them right now, or you can do it later also. So, when you look at your chart, basically, let's go to the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when you look at your chart, this is the North Indian system of, making a horoscope. You kind of open any,
Dr. Karan Mittal: For now, or if you have a printed community from the past, that's also fine enough. You kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: put your birth date, birthplace, and also the birth time into that particular section. These are the three things that are necessary. A name, gender, etc. is more for the Murata perspective, but for predictive astrology, these are the three things that are necessary. Once you insert these things, and of course, if you're
Dr. Karan Mittal: belonging to some foreign country, then you'll have to see the daylight season at that point of time, if it's a winter time or something of that sort. So, you'll have to adjust, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: the place, so that will tell you the longitudes and latitudes of a particular place that you're born in. So you put it on… you can use apps like Only, you can use apps like AstroSage, there are many apps that are available that give you a free literature. Once you do that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then the first chart that opens, it's also called as the Lagna chart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So, the Lagna chart is basically that photograph that we were talking about. Now, when you look at the Lagna chart, you will see that there are 12 houses. In a sense, these quaterilaterals that you're seeing, and the triangles that are… that we are seeing, are called as houses.
Dr. Karan Mittal: each house kind of signifies a particular trait in our lives, okay? So, like, the first chart could be about my physical body, the second house could be my family and the money that my family owns, the third could be my brother. So, so different… different houses kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Hold characteristics of different aspects of your life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, you'll see these numbers.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? In every box, or in every triangle, you see a number. It starts from a particular number in the, in this house, in this first house, or if I'm not, I think…
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I've been using them, use them.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so this is the North Indian system of, making a chart, and… and you will see that there are 12 sections in this chart, okay? Few are like boxes, like squares, and few are like triangles. And every box over here, or every section over here, holds
Dr. Karan Mittal: a trait for a certain aspect of your life, or holds the characteristics of a certain aspect of your life. And then the second part that you see is the number.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, this number usually stands for the zodiac sign, or the dashi, and you will see that there's one particular number in the first box that you see. This is the first box.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You'll see a particular number, and after that number, the house… all the numbers go in an anti-clockwise direction. You'll see that from 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, it just goes in an anti-clockwise direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this number, basically, which is there in this first box, is basically called as your Ladina Rashi, or your Lagna Zodiac.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: The number that is there in this first box in your chart is basically your Lagna sign, or the Lagna zodiac, or the Lagna Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then… and then, of course, you have to look at your whole chart. We'll come to what is Laguna and Chandra Rashi, but just for understanding perspective, look at your whole chart, and then go to the place where Moon is there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So Moon in English, Chandra in Sanskrit or Hindi. So go to the place where moon is there, and see the number that is there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay?
Dr. Karan Mittal: in the box, or in the triangle where moon is there. That is your Chandra Rashi. Of course, it's too basic, but for people who are new to astrology, it would help. So… so we see the number that is kind of there in the first house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And we also see the number that is there in the, that… where the moon is situated. So here, 7 is the number which is for the first house, okay, the Tula Rashi, the Libra sign.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And 1 is the number when Moon is there, so that is the Aries or Meishra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, the first house… number becomes your Lagina Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the number where the moon is situated becomes a Chandra Rashi, or the moon center.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, for just taking another example, for this chart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The sixth number is in the first house, okay? So that's the Laguna Rashi Kanya, okay? And the moon is in the
Dr. Karan Mittal: Moon is situated in this house, okay, and the number over here is 10, so that becomes your
Dr. Karan Mittal: 10 dollars. Okay, come on, go ahead.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, just, just make a note of the Laguna number and the Chandra number for you. We'll come to the numbers, what it means, etc. later, maybe tomorrow's session. But for now, just make a note of it. If you don't have your honors book right now, maybe you could do it after the session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so what is the lag now?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, lagna is basically, if I go from pure, pure astrological analysis, Lagna is basically how the world perceives you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: how is your body? Okay, so basically it stands for your whole body, in total, and also how the world perceives you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Lagna Rashi, whatever… we'll come to what those numbers means, but whatever the first house is signifying for your particular house, for your particular chart, that means how the world sees you or perceives you as a person. So that's the Lagna Rashi. It's basically…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the sign, so when a person is born, it's basically the sign that is kind of rising at the exact east in a particular location. So if I'm born in Mumbai at 1PM,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe 15th, like, the data between 15th November 2000. So, at that particular point of time, at 1PM, the zodiac that was rising in the east becomes your Lagna ration. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Exactly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In Mumbai at 1PM on 15th November 2000, in the east direction, the zodiac that was present, that becomes the Lagna Rashi of the particular person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And at that same time, at that particular time, the place, or the rashi, or the zodiac, where the moon was situated, okay, that becomes your Chandra Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Soap?
Dr. Karan Mittal: At 1PM, what was rising in the east becomes the Lagunarashi, and at that point of time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: wherever the moon was situated, that becomes a Chandra Rashi, okay? So that's basically how it is. Now, what are Rashis? We'll come to it tomorrow, and we'll discuss it in a bit, what are Rashis? But for now, we need to understand that Laguna is basically
Dr. Karan Mittal: How the world perceives you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And also, it is the sign that is rising at the east direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: at the time you were born. And that's why the place is important. Probably for Mumbai, at 1PM, the sign was something else, but for Kolkata, the sign was something else. So that's why the place, the longitude and the latitude of the particular, birth chart are important, because for every place, it changes at same time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, that's how the world perceives.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And your Rashi is basically your psyche. In Shastras, in Indian school of thought, of course, moon is said to be the, you know, kind of one that determines your mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, and that's why… that's why Soma is related to Manava. So, your Chandra Rashi, the Rashi where the moon is situated, is basically your
Dr. Karan Mittal: the one that determines your mind, the characteristics of your mind, the how you function internally is your Chandra Gashima. So, lagna is how the world perceives you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And?
Dr. Karan Mittal: how the mind is internal, or… so it's a… this is more objective, and this is more subjective, like, it's kind of internal to you. So that's the Chandra Rashi, and both can be completely different.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, maybe…
Dr. Karan Mittal: maybe let's… let's do a small exercise, maybe for all of us, and for people especially who are new to astrology. I want you to kind of take a few minutes, maybe, like, 5 minutes, and write down a few words that… what are… what are the words, or what are your characteristics, the way the world sees you, okay?
Dr. Karan Mittal: And what are the characteristics, like, your internal being, how does that feel? So the world might look at me as maybe outgoing, you know, kind of extrovert, speaking loudly, talkative.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But internally, probably I'm a shy, maybe a docile, or passive person. So let's kind of try to understand what's a lag now, and then we'll correlate it with the astrological chart tomorrow, or as a homework. So it would be an interesting exercise to kind of see
Dr. Karan Mittal: How does the world perceive you? What's your understanding? What people have told you about how you are?
Dr. Karan Mittal: How do you feel in your inner well-being? Let's take 5 minutes, and let's try to kind of understand that, and we'll take questions also. Namanji has raised his hand.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, that means you can unmute and speak.
Naman Kashyap: Yeah, so, sir, I just wanted to check, is it that it has to be different? The world might perceive me, and inside also I'm the same, so that is also fine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's say it's possible, it's highly possible, but as a psychologist also, we have different masks that we wear with the world, and internally we are different, so it can be… it's definitely possible from all the astrological and also psychological perspective, but
Dr. Karan Mittal: I would… I would request you to take an… take an honest reflection first, and if it's the same, then it's same. It's definitely possible. Your Lagna, Chandra, she can also listen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Professor Jeep?
R PRASATH KUMAR: Jinamaste.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Namaste.
R PRASATH KUMAR: One clarification. This lagna signifies the person's body or the personality.
Dr. Karan Mittal: both. Body also and personality also, but because we are now… this course is more about the psychological aspect, astro-psychology and was too. I spoke about the personality. So, yes, it signifies the body also.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Okay, thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So let's take 5 minutes, and please make your own reflections, and it would be an interesting thing when you correlate it with the findings tomorrow. So don't skip this part at least. Go with more of how you feel.
Dr. Karan Mittal: About these two questions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We're done with that part, and I'll also leave you with one question, which is the third question which you can see on your slide. What does that gap cost you?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Once you're done with your answers, you can probably message me on the… so that I know… again, because I cannot see many of you, and know how much to wait and how much to…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you have a question, you can ask follow-up.
K Shubham: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: just raising ideas and friends. Yes.
K Shubham: So, regarding these remedies that you said, so if someone does a remedy, and let's say it mitigates some of his karma, then will that karma come back later in life?
Dr. Karan Mittal: No. So, it doesn't happen that way. When you're dealing with… of course, we'll come to this question, but since we have time, once you're dealing with mandar, karma, etc, when you do a remedy, you are creating an equal opposite force, right? So, you're also pacifying the karma by doing a remedy, whether it's a japa, dhana.
Dr. Karan Mittal: couple, etc. So, we are kind of doing that penance that needs to counteract that particular dosha or that kind of problem, so it doesn't come back there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'll just wait for a minute so that you can answer the question, what does that gap cost you? And then we can take it forward.
K Shubham: Okay, so one more question we can ask, meanwhile…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, sure.
K Shubham: Yeah, so you said that remedies work, but then it sounds a little contradicting, because you have a chart, and that tells you something, but then you do remedies, so it's kind of counteracting that. So, how do two things coexist?
Dr. Karan Mittal: There's no contradiction at all.
Dr. Karan Mittal: When you talk about the Pradava.
Dr. Karan Mittal: As I said, the product is divided into Manda, Tibra, and… sorry, Manda Maddam, and Tibra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, the Manda Pradavas, Shastriji and the Madhya Prabhavdhas also, Shastriji, can be counteracted, or can be classified by a remedy. Otherwise, it will… otherwise, the chart becomes a victim, right? It becomes a verdict that there's nothing that can be changed. This is what you have to go through the life. So, it's not as… as…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, kind of, like, if it becomes a verdict, then you cannot do anything. Then what's the role of free will, and what's the role of Triyaman Karma, etc. So, it's a more dynamic balance that runs between two.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If it's a Tibura Paraducta, then of course we cannot counteract that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, speaking from a very Shasta perspective. But it's not… it's not a contradiction. That's the role of free will, bro.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In fact, you asked this to Govindra once he takes this out. Okay, so I think few people are done, so let's move ahead so that we don't… maybe if you're not done with the question, you can reflect it after the session. Also, probably open your charts and see the numbers that are
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, kind of there in the Lagna Rashi… sorry, the Lagna house, and also provided the Chandra Rashi, whichever it is. Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, you don't need to message me privately, you can keep your answers to yourself. I just wanted to understand if everyone's done. Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, basically, your lagna is,
Dr. Karan Mittal: The main door to your horoscope, or the main door,
Dr. Karan Mittal: To you. The world… the world sees you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: through this lagana, okay? So… so I can look, like, even the physical, like, someone asked, is it… is it also the physical body? Yes, it's the physical body, because the world sees the physical body first, whether I am tall, I am… I'm short, I'm thin, I am obese, I am, like, dark, or I am white, or I'm fair. So the world kind of sees
Dr. Karan Mittal: that first. So, lagna also means your physical body and your physical appearance, because that's how the world perceives you first. And then also, the subtle level of Lagna is how the world sees you as a person. So, lagna is basically the door to your personality is also the door to your chart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that's why the Lagna holds so much of importance in Indian astrology, because it gives you, like, the Lagna and the Chandra Rashi itself can allow you to understand your inner traits, your characteristics, etc, fully. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's how the main, that's Lugna, that's the goal to you. Now, combining it with WAS2,
Dr. Karan Mittal: The main door of your house also signifies
Dr. Karan Mittal: the way your horoscope affects you, or the vastru affects you. And that's why, when we do the… when we do the Vastu part of this course, we'll see that how much importance has been given to the main door, the Mahadwar of the house, because it shows… or the first thing that a person sees, looks at, is basically at the Mahadwar, or the gate while he's entering at the house. And it's not just the person, it's also
Dr. Karan Mittal: you. So, that's why in Shastas, it was given so much importance, because that's the place where you leave behind whatever has happened in the outside world, and enter into a place where it's more personal and more intimate to you. So, main door was given too much of importance. In fact, in Vastu.
Dr. Karan Mittal: 30-40% of the positivity of the house can just come if the main road is in the auspicious direction as per Vasta Shastra. So that's Lagna.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's how the world sees you, and the lagna of your house, or the main door of your house, is basically the auspicious part that helps you enter from the outer world to the inner world. And what is Chandra Dashi?
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's the… it's the… it's the room that's inside you. It's what's happening inside you. So that's the Chandra Rashi. In this sense, how you feel, how you operate internally, what's your cognitive aspect, rational aspect, emotional aspect, how deep you are, how superficial you are, how you think. Everything that we speak about in the modern scientific language as the psychology.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or, or as a cognition, or the neurology, everything comes from the Chandra. So, Chandra, basically, and that's why
Dr. Karan Mittal: In Indian astrology, or in the Bhatia Jyotes, Chandra has been given the role of mana, or the mind, because Chandra is, like, fast-moving. It's the fastest-moving planet, and our mind is also like, right? It moves quickly, it doesn't…
Dr. Karan Mittal: stays stable for minutes, or maybe even seconds, or maybe even days. So that's why Chandra has been attributed the designation for the one who controls the mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, that's between the Chandra and the Chandra Rashi. And also, Arishis also knew that, you know? So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what you could see… what you could say is the houses that we saw, that one, the houses that bosses.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That we saw.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just angling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's stupid.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah. These boxes that we saw are probably different rooms on a particular floor, and every room has a particular attribute. Like, one could be this room where you sleep, one could be the kitchen where you cook, one could be probably the washroom where you fresh up. So, it has different, different functions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the rashis are basically how the room is made internally, okay? So, a particular house or a particular bedroom could have yellow walls, could have blue walls, could have black walls. So, rashi basically gives flavor to this particular room, okay? So, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: One is the characteristics and the traits, and the Rashi kind of giving it flavors. So, probably now in the Nagana house, there is the sixth Rashi, or the Kanya Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, the body, or the way this person deals with the outer world, will be like the Kenya Rashu, okay? This person will deal with the outer world like Tulah Rashu, or the Libra sign. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: it will give the flavors that are needed, okay? Now, my wishes also understood that the whole world cannot be classified into 12 simple rashis. So then, of course, they went further, and they divided all the rashis, or all the 12 rashis, further into 27 nakshatras. So it's like…
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of going more deeper into understanding the Dagna, understanding the Chandagashi, etc. So, the rishis divided these 12 rashis further into the 27 akshatras that you will see tomorrow. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: a person… suppose, let's kind of say, look at this particular chart. So, a person who's having Meish, or Aries as standard Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: all the people in the world who have Chandra as… or who have Meisha as their Chandarashi need not have similar characteristics, because in the Chandrashe itself, there are around two… around three different nakshatras that further signify different flavors to that particular Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we dealt with three things today. One is the Levna Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: One is the Chandra Rashi, and then the concept of nakshatar, which is, like, further, deeper concept to the Rashi itself. And then, then there is a fourth concept that probably we did on the day three, is the Dasha concept. Now, now, dasha…
Dr. Karan Mittal: is basically different time periods, or different years that a particular planet influences you. So, a particular point of your life, the sun would be more influential. A particular point of your life, the Moon will be more influential.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Mars will be more inflated. It keeps on changing, and different planets have different numbers of years. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Every planet will put influence on you for different, different points of time, and during that point of time, the characteristics of that planet will start, kind of.
Dr. Karan Mittal: opening up in your life. So if you're… if you're… suppose if your Sun, or if your Jupiter is kind of signifying something very auspicious for you, and currently you are going into the
Dr. Karan Mittal: Currently, your… that particular period when Jupiter is more influential on our life is functional. Definitely, it will…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, kind of push your progress, or kind of make your progress meaningful, and that's what I spoke about in the initial part. It tells you how to align your commercial. In that particular point of time, that person gets into a business, or something where he earns, or something where he teaches, related to whatever is
Dr. Karan Mittal: horoscope is kind of signifying, he will attain
Dr. Karan Mittal: faster progress, and many-fold progress in that particular aspect of his life. So, so, so one is the basic trait that we saw in the charts, then the timings of the trait, okay? The timings of the trait, and when each trait, that is the dasha system, and then, of course, there is nakshatras, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: Chandrahis, which kind of give you a feel of your psyche in a deeper and a more congruent way.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's… that's about, the Jyotesha part and the, the Lagna and the Chandra Dashi part. Now, what do we need, from all of you for the next few days? It's first, kind of having your Lagna chart
Dr. Karan Mittal: with you, in the sense, take a piece of paper, or, like, every time opening an app probably might not work, because we might also correlate it with the vast flow of your house, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So you kind of take,
Dr. Karan Mittal: a page and make your learner chart in the same way that's there on the screen. And also, probably look for the layout of your house, and then kind of also try to, like, find the direction where, what it is. And also, we'll also see how to kind of find the direction in the right way, but also kind of searching the layout of the house. Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Aw.
Dr. Karan Mittal: COVID from Virginia Brazil?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, any questions until we have Roland Prabhji on the book? Any questions
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, tomorrow's and the session thereafter will be more detailed and, like, longer. This is more like an introduction to the home team. Yes, Namanjit?
Naman Kashyap: So, I read in many questions, but I think there was one line yet pinned it from Monday, so as it in the small or in the vast. So, is it the same concept which we discuss in psychology that, you know, we attract those kind of persons?
Naman Kashyap: Which we are inside, and the many power of manifestation, that, you know, if you're manifesting something, then… So, the modern psychology which says these two things, is it coming from there, sir?
Dr. Karan Mittal: See, modern psychology actually doesn't speak about it, but yes, that's the same concept, the way you resonate internally.
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of also the ripples spread around you, and kind of attract similar kind of people, and vice versa also. So, if you change your internal core, things will change externally, and you need to change your external core, you kind of change things internally. So, if you surround yourself with good people.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you will slowly, like, you will also start transforming, and, of course, the opposite is also equally true. But, yeah, it's similar to the law of attraction and manifestation, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Shubamzu.
K Shubham: So, what is the time sensitivity of the chart?
K Shubham: If we know what, like, in what approximation we can ignore, like, seconds, minutes?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so basic lagna chart approximately stays the same for the 2 hours.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But, because…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, 24 hours divided by 12, there are 12 washes, so every Lagna approximately stays on the east direction for 12 hours… oh, sorry, for 2 hours. That's the basic Lagna chart. But as you go into more time-sensitive KP and time-sensitive,
Dr. Karan Mittal: astrology, then this sensitivity keeps on, reducing. Like, there are… it changes even every two, three minutes, it changes every minute, depends on, what… how much depth you are going
Dr. Karan Mittal: In a particular chart. So… so that's… that's what I can tell you. It changes as per the depth the astrologist looks at a chart width. So, lagna chart, to our sensitivity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Approximately. But it also sometimes happens is, you know, suppose you're born at the… at 12pm, and at 12 PM… around 12pm, at 12 PM, probably, the lagna is changing, okay? It's changing from Aries to probably, Rishab. So, if you're 5 minutes zero there, then your lagna chart will change.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's how complex it is, yeah.
K Shubham: Is there a standard way to verify that? Because,
K Shubham: I mean, what happens is that I have visited some astrologists, and they tend to justify everything which I say.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so there are methods to kind of correct your time astrologically. There are no methods, like, of course, astrologically we do Prishna charts, and there's a… there's a time correction method in Christianity astrology, where we try to find out the approximate time that you were born, and there are methods to do that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So yes, there are methods in Astrologic also currently there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because even during that time, it was not, you know, like, getting to the right time because of homework, da-da-da. So there are methods to look, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, we have Krishna… so, we have Krishna, Chandra, Sundrami, you can ask a question, and then we have…
Krishna Chandra Subramani: Rabhook, so people who are, like, C-sectioned by birth, if their parents plan to get a good chart, how does that work astrologically?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What did you say?
Krishna Chandra Subramani: if someone, like, if they plan that their child would get a good chart and have a C-section birth, like, they plan the correct time so that they would get a good chart, is that possible? How does that work?
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's a gray area of astrology. Usually in these times, then the time of conceptualization holds more importance than the fertilization of the egg happen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, both the charts become equally,
Dr. Karan Mittal: functional in that particular person's order. So you cannot trick the parameters in so easily. So, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So if… so… so the time of conceptualization chart is also looked at, okay? And then there is another chart which is called as the 7th month chart, that also comes… like, it becomes a bit complicated, but basically it's… it's not that easy to trick the horoscope, yeah.
Krishna Chandra Subramani: Okay, purple 90.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
K Shubham: What time is considered, Projit? Basically, is it time when the child comes out, or when umbilical cord is cut? Is there something…
Dr. Karan Mittal: physical cord is cut, because that's the time where you connect with the outer world, right?
K Shubham: Okay, so then it can be, like, 3-4 minutes after the child has come out.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, yeah.
K Shubham: And what happens if two people have same birth time, and around approximately same location?
K Shubham: Let's say… born in the same city at same time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So even… even… there is… even a different of few seconds, of course, probably changes the horoscope, and also, there are other things also, the conceptualization also plays an important role, and that's why,
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, that… that sanskara also, what kind of… you know, we saw a proper nakshatra, proper day, etc, to do that with Han sanskara, because that also played an equal and important role. So, of course, they might have very similar lives, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But even a few seconds of difference, like, it's in… I don't know, maybe Go and Prabhu can verify this, when Mahara and Bhima, and Rudyolan are said to be born on the same day.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But they had different lives. So, so, only the places were different. They were… Bhima was in the jungle a lot longer than it was in the palace. So, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so that's what I've read in some book. So, it changes depending on the play. It's a few seconds here and there, it changes, the microcharms.
K Shubham: Because for 12…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, your karma also kind of wills. That's what I said, the second part of the astrology.
K Shubham: like, the twins, generally, they have very different nature, so… but that's, like, they should have similar… at least Lagna's side should have been similar.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so that's what micro astrology, even 1 or 2 minutes of difference, makes a huge difference, or… Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so… and also the younger kid has… is considered the… like, if it's a… like, twin birth itself is… is a very complicated topic in astrology, and there are different ways of looking at it. The younger child is usually considered the older one. The one who's born later is considered the older one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that's… that also holds in, again, now coming from Shastras, Lakshmanji and Shatragnaji, both… so, both were twins, and both had different lives. So… so, yeah. So there are injunctions and Shastras to that also, how to find that, yeah.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Karanji, namaste.
Dr. Karan Mittal: G.
R PRASATH KUMAR: So, based on today's discussion, my understanding is
R PRASATH KUMAR: The lagna says about the personality, the appearance, and also the gunas also. Character.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. How the world… basically everything that… how the world looks at you. Whether it's a guna as a person can look at me, maybe tell me I'm more of a Tamsed guna, like, how the world kind of looks at you. Yes.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Then the, Rashi talks about the moon, Which is the mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Nope.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
R PRASATH KUMAR: I mean…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So rushed.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Can we conclude that, based on the, Rashi, their mind functions, right?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Beautiful.
R PRASATH KUMAR: That is the case. My doubt is, each Rashi have Three kind of stars.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Each star's ruled by a different planet.
R PRASATH KUMAR: So, how that combination works?
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's one. You have a bigger flavor, like, you have a base note of that particular rashi, like in a perfume, probably. You have a base note of Chandan, but probably then you might have a minor note of Kasturi into it, which kind of changes the whole, you know, the basic feel of that chandan, or you might have minor note of mas…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry, more into it. So that's how it changes, you…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you might have… so, I could…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe let me take an example.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I could be balanced, like, more like a Libra, Tula, Rashi, I could be balanced, but when I'm kind of flavored with Mongol, then that I will have an aggressive need to balance things. If it is flavored with probably Jupiter, I would have a more calmer and
Dr. Karan Mittal: peaceful need to balance things. So it changes, like, the balance is there, but the way the balance is flavored kind of changes, yeah.
R PRASATH KUMAR: So… That sounds like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Theology also speaks, sir.
R PRASATH KUMAR: So, so the probability comes, like, 12… no, 27… into four.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Because each star has each quarter.
R PRASATH KUMAR: So, 1 or 8 different categories of 12 races, correct?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, that's… that's why one… yeah, 108… like, one of the astronomical reasons why 108 is so auspicious is this 2784, yeah.
R PRASATH KUMAR: So this 108 part of each quarter of each star.
R PRASATH KUMAR: when have different combination with 12 rashays. So, again, 12 into 108. So that number of probabilities will happen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then 12 houses also, so it will keep on changing.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Okay, thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's like, we had done it, we tried doing it, like, it's beyond the number of permutations and combinations that can come. And it's not just 12, no? The permutations and combinations will keep on changing.
R PRASATH KUMAR: 10. Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Not just multiplication, it's like the permutation formula that you left off.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Just one more note to add.
R PRASATH KUMAR: Bhima and Duryodhana… Duryodhana was one day older, say, approximately 12 hours
R PRASATH KUMAR: So, one day, Elder Duryodhana, one day younger is Bhima.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so that's what I… that's what I said. I'm not an expert on it. Go into who might, clarify on it. What I had read in an astrological… a chart which analyzed both the charts said that both were one and the same. So there are charts of Bhagwan Rama, Bhagwan Krishna Hetzaka, and a few books.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Approximate charts, as per what shathers speak. So, they said the charts were similar, and they were born on the same. So, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so thank you for clarifying that. Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, fine. So, no more questions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, maybe going through June?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so maybe we can… we can stop for the day, and we can… we can probably continue tomorrow on… in a longer day, in a longer session. And also I would request you to have your charts and your layouts, if possible, by tomorrow.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
K Shubham: Privacy, where can we get the site?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, for people, of course, I'll post a few, you know, images, a few links, a few apps, free apps on the group, like Astro Stage is one app, there's another app called Only Week. These are free apps that are available. If you want to download it on,
Dr. Karan Mittal: on yellow dome.
Dr. Karan Mittal: laptop, then there are also free apps there also available, so you can… you just need to know your birthday, birth time, birthplace. Just feed the details, and your charts will be generated. So there are many free apps available. I'll post a few Google Play Storements on the… on the… on the
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. Yes, the recordings will be available. Vidur will, coordinate the uploading of recording, and you can access it, through your login ID on the Vidor tomorrow. Okay, so we can kind of end here, and… and see you on tomorrow.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: A strategy?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Nona, do you have a question?
Naman Kashyap: Yeah, just wanted to check, sir, like, I mean, what is the… what would be the sequence of the next 4 days? Like, today was the introduction, so do we have… is it something planned? I mean, maybe that might be helpful.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so we have more intense of astrology tomorrow and day 3, and day 3 onwards, we start with, like, half of the half part of the day 3 will start with last two of your particular house.
Naman Kashyap: Okay.
Naman Kashyap: So, for more…
Dr. Karan Mittal: More of getting deeper into the astro and vasta of your own charts and other houses.
Naman Kashyap: And I just had a question, I thought going through will come, so they didn't ask at that time. So what happens, like, the example which you gave, that, you know, Rishi's had told that South May, you should not have much windows? And now you gave the example, which makes sense of that fact.
Naman Kashyap: Many times it happens that, you know, we do not know the reasons of something.
Naman Kashyap: If, suppose, today you… I didn't know this fact, that this logic is there, if you would not have told, then, you know, if… even if, you know, someone else would have told without the reason, then it's difficult to believe it.
Naman Kashyap: So, my actual question is that, to what extent, then, I mean, like, I should believe something or not believe something, the Shaddap Praman. Unless all Shaddaprahman, if it cannot be…
Naman Kashyap: corroborated with the Pratakshraman, so… so ultimately, that is a question, then.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So I think you ask it to go improve tomorrow, it might be a better answer, and then I'll supplement with my answer to the question, I guess.
Naman Kashyap: Okay, okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Really cute.
K Shubham: Can astrology tell, like, how much effort a person should put for a certain thing in life?
K Shubham: It might tell that, okay, something is good or bad, but can it also kind of quantify it so that one doesn't go on putting out so much effort that, like, only that part of life he is focusing and rest is left out? That kind of thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: it doesn't quantify it for you, because then it will take it… take a free will away. It kind of tells you that this is difficult, then this is easier, and then it depends on your free will to kind of… how much… like, probably in someone's horoscope, probably
Dr. Karan Mittal: Doing a post-graduation course is not possible, but if he's so determined, and if he puts in his efforts, then it's his choice. Like, of course, the charts will say what they are saying.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But it depends. Also, a person might, who believes too much might say, okay, Tikiv, it's so, so difficult, then I'll give it, and I'll look for some other, other, probably, career. So, so it depends, like, how much you want to put in as an effort.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But it doesn't quantify it for you. There's no way to quantify it here.
K Shubham: But then, how do you know, like, practically, if you have to use this, then how do you know when to stop? Like, let's say for post-adjustment itself, it could be some exam, or it could be some, let's say, career, or it could be some health-related issue. How do you know now you should give up and just accept it?
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's more of a balance of, I think, more of your personal insight, and also your psychology, and also maybe an astrological guidance. I think it cannot be… these kind of decisions cannot just be taken on one aspect of astrology, you know? It also depends on how much
Dr. Karan Mittal: How willing you are, how much exhausted you are, how much burnt out you are, to kind of invest, that much time and effort in a particular field.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So some people, suppose… some people who have that kind of rashi, which is very determined and aggressive, etc, despite,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whatever.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the astrologist says they keep on doing it, they keep on doing it, that chat speaks about it, that they will not leave something so easy. And some people just give up, even without the action. So that also the chat speaks. So… so astrological probability is not just about that event or situation at all, it is also based on
Dr. Karan Mittal: your particular disposition to kind of approach. So, astrologer knows, like, astronomers, while looking at it, they also tell you that, okay, you have less possibility, but you have this nature, and you'll keep on trying, trying, trying, trying, etc. So, probably.
Dr. Karan Mittal: three years down the line, this yoga can come, but are you willing to wait for 3 years? All that things come, so tying, your psyche, etc. Many things become more complicated as you approach complicated questions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then we try to look at… so suppose marriage is not someone's in someone's start. Then he's very determined to get married. Then we see, okay, 2020, 2029, there's… until then, we don't see a possibility. 2030,
Dr. Karan Mittal: it's possible. Are you willing to wait until then? So… so that factor comes in, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that the possibility is changing, as per the shares.
Dr. Karan Mittal: No.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Fine. So, thank you, everyone, and I'll see you tomorrow, along with Govan, probably for the session. Yes.
Naman Kashyap: Thank you, buddy. I think you should know.